Guide to the Max Shachtman Papers TAM.103
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series V: International bulletins, periodicals, and other documents
  - PART A: LEFT OPPOSITION BULLETINS
    - Bulletin de la Ligue Communiste Internationaliste(B.L.) (in French) published by the International Secretariat, Oct 1933-Jan 1934 (Box 42, Folder 11)
    - Mitteilungsblatt-Bolschewike-Leninisten- Austria (in German), ca.1933 (Box 42, Folder 12)
    - Documents et Discussion (in French) Supplement and Bulletin of le Secretariat de la. Ligue Communiste Internationale (B.L.), Jan 1934-Feb 1934 (Box 42, Folder 13)
    - Informationsbrief- Geman - published by the International Section of IKD (in German), Jun 1934 (Box 42, Folder 14)
    - Bulletin Interieur de la Ligue Communiste- French section (in German), Jul 1934 (Box 42, Folder 15)
    - Bulletin Interieur de la Ligue Communiste(in French), Jul 1934-Aug 1934 (Box 42, Folder 16)
    - Bulletin International Jeunesses B.L.(in French), Aug 1931 (Box 42, Folder 17)
    - I nternational Bulletin of the League of Communist Internationalists- published for Communist League of Americans by I.S. (in English), Apr 1934, Sep 1934 (Box 42, Folder 18)
    - International Bulletin of the Youth(in German), Nov 1934-May 1935 (Box 42, Folder 19)
    - Bulletin Interieur B/L SFIO(in French), Dec 1934-May 1936 (Box 43, Folder 1)
      Microfilm Reel Number 52
    - International Bulletin(in English), Dec 1934-Jan 1935 (Box 43, Folder 2)
    - Bulletin Interieur de la L.C.T.(in French), Mar 1935-May 1935 (Box 43, Folder 3)
    - International Jugend-Bulletin(in German), Apr 1935-Aug 1935 (Box 43, Folder 4)
    - Bulletin de la Ligue de Comunistes Internationalists B.L.(in French), May 1935-Dec 1935 (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Jugend Korrespondenz(in German), undated (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - International Jugend - Information(in German), Jul 1935-Sep 1935, Jan 1936-Mar 1936 (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - L.E.I. (B-L) Service de Presse(in French), Jul 17, 1935 (Box 43, Folder 8)
    - New Tribune Discussion Page of IKC (BL)(in German), Nov 1935 (Box 43, Folder 9)
    - Bulletin d'Information et de Presse sur L'U.R.S.S. L.C.I. (B-L)(in French), Jan 1936-May 1936 (Box 43, Folder 10)
    - Nouvelles D'U.R.S.S.(in French), Mar 1936-Jan 1937 (Box 43, Folder 11)
      Microfilm Reel Number 52 (Reel 53 begins within folder 11 with September 1936)
    - Union Commmiste - Bulletin d'Information et de Liason, Apr 1936 (Box 43, Folder 12)
      Microfilm Reel Number 53
    - Bulletin de la Ligue des Communistes-Internationalists (B-L)(in French), May 1936 (Box 43, Folder 13)
    - Bolletino d'Informazione(in Italian), Jun 1936, Aug 1936 (Box 43, Folder 14)
    - L'organe de Masse(in French), Jun 1936 (Box 43, Folder 15)
    - Bulletin Interieur du P.O.I.(B-L) (in French), Jun 1936-Feb 1939 (Box 43, Folder 16)
    - Service d'Information et de Presse(I.S. of the F.I.) (in French), Sep 1936-Nov 1938 (Box 43, Folder 17)
    - Bulletin Interieur Parti Socialiste Revolutionaire(in French), Nov 1936-Jan 1938 (Box 43, Folder 18)
      Microfilm Reel Number 54
    - Press Information Service for the Fourth International(in English), Apr 1905 (Box 43, Folder 19)
    - Bulletin d'Information Interieur P.O.I.- (in French), Jan 15, 1937 (Box 43, Folder 20)
    - Deutsches Bulletin der Bolshevistisch-Leninlischen-Spanien(in German - pub. in Spain) 4th International, Apr 1937 (Box 43, Folder 21)
    - Bulletin Francais; de la Section B-L d'Espagne, undated (Box 43, Folder 22)
    - Information Bulletin (International Bureau in the F.T.) (in English), Jul 1937 (Box 43, Folder 23)
    - Informatie-en Discussie Bulletin -International Secretariat (in Dutch), Jul 1937 (Box 43, Folder 24)
    - Information Partido Marxista Revolucionaria Argentina, 4th International(in Spanish), Oct 1937 (Box 43, Folder 25)
    - International Internal Bulletin(I.S. of 4th International), Apr 1938 (Box 43, Folder 26)
    - Internes International Bulletin - I.S. of the 4th International(in German), undated (Box 44, Folder 1)
      Microfilm Reel Number 55
    - Bulletin Interieur International - I.S. of the 4th International(in French), Apr 1938-Jun 1938 (Box 44, Folder 2)
    - Circulaire du Secretariat International - 4th International(in French), undated (Box 44, Folder 3)
    - Mitteilung S-Blatt der I.K.D.(in German), Sep 1938 (Box 44, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence Internationaliste - for the construction of the 4th international (in French), Aug 1939-Apr 1940 (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - Bulletin de la 4'eme Internationale(in French), Sep 1939 (Box 44, Folder 6)
      Microfilm Reel Number 56
    - Contre Le Courant Bulletin du Groupe Communiste Internationaliste- pour la construction de la IV Int'l, Dec 1939-Mar 1940 (Box 44, Folder 7)
    - Discussion Bulletin of R.C.P.(Britain) (in English), May 1940-Jun 1940 (Box 44, Folder 8)
    - Bulletin du Secretariat Europien de la IV Int'l(in French), Aug 1945 (Box 44, Folder 9)
    - The Revolutionary Communist(For Members Only) South Africa, Nov 1945 (Box 44, Folder 10)
    - Groupe Comuniste-Internationaliste (Trotskyiste) Bulletin Information- Pour La IVth Int'l (in French), Nov 12, 1945 (Box 44, Folder 11)
    - Bulletin Interieur Secretariat International(in French), May 1947-Sep 1950 (Box 44, Folder 12)
      Microfilm Reel Number 57
    - Internal Bulletin- pub.by IS of 4th Int'l (in English), Dec 1947 (Box 44, Folder 13)
    - L'Internationaliste - Bulletin Interieur de fraction Belge de la gauche(in French), Dec 1947-May 1948 (Box 44, Folder 14)
    - The Russian Question - Bulletin of the Irish Section (in English), Mar 1948 (Box 44, Folder 15)
    - L'Internationaliste - Documents de la fraction Belge de la gauche Communiste Internationals(in French), Oct 1948 (Box 44, Folder 16)
    - Democratic Proletarienne Bulletin de liaison et information(in French), Feb 1952 (Box 44, Folder 17)
    - Bulletin Interieur de P.C.I.(in French), ca.1950 (Box 44, Folder 18)
    - Informations Internationales(in French), Apr 1962 (Box 44, Folder 19)
  - PART B: INTERNAL BULLETIN OF U.S.A. - Groups
    - Internal Bulletin of the C.L.A. (opposition)(handwritten note reads: "folder # omitted" - does this mean the # on the film, or the folder? Check microfilm reel), 1933-1934 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - The Bulletin- Young Communist and Young Communist League, Feb 26, 1934 (Box 45, Folder 2)
      Microfilm Reel Number 58
    - Internal Bulletin- pub. by the Organizing Committee of the Socialist Party Convention, 1937-Dec 1937 (Box 45, Folder 3)
    - In Defense of Bolshevist - Leninist League, 1938-1939 (Box 45, Folder 4)
    - Internal Bulletin Socialist Workers Party - "State Capitalism and World Revolution" by Johnson and Forest, 1938-1946, 1950 (Box 45, Folder 5)
    - Young Socialist Review - Young Peoples Socialist League, 1939-1963 (Box 45, Folder 6)
      Microfilm Reel Number 59
    - The Bulletin- Leninist League, Oct 1939-Nov 1939 (Box 46, Folder 1)
    - Internal Bulletin- Workers Party, Apr 1940-Nov 1940 (Box 46, Folder 2)
      Microfilm Reel Number 60
    - Special Bulletin on S.W.P.- League for a Revolutionary Workers Party, Apr 1940 (Box 46, Folder 3)
      Microfilm Reel Number 61
    - International Bulletin no. 1- American Committee for the 4th International, Apr 1940 (Box 46, Folder 4)
    - Educational Bulletin- Workers Party, Jul 1, 1942-Aug 1, 1942 (Box 46, Folder 5)
    - Bulletin of the Workers Party, 1943-1947 (Box 46, Folder 6)
    - Education- Bulletin of the National Education Department Workers Party, Oct 1945-Nov 1945 (Box 46, Folder 7)
      Microfilm Reel Number 62
    - International Information Bulletin, Mar 1947 (Box 47, Folder 1)
    - Socialist Views Discussion Bulletin- Libertarian Socialist League, 1951-1952 (Box 47, Folder 2)
    - Y.P.S.L.-S.Y.L. Joint Discussion Bulletin, Jan 10, 1954-Jan 12, 1954 (Box 47, Folder 3)
    - Left Wing Bulletin- Left Wing caucus of the Young Socialist League, Mar 1957-Jul 1957 (Box 47, Folder 4)
    - Workers Power- Workers Party of Maryland, ca.1967 (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - PART C: PERIODICALS OF THE LEFT OPPOSITION
    - Arbeiterbriefe/Arbeiter Printed in Czechoslovakia (in German), Dec 1933 (Box 47, Folder 6)
    - L'Action Socialiste- Section Belge de la IV Int'l (in French), Jun 13, 1940 (Box 47, Folder 7)
    - L'Appel(in French), ca.1937 (Box 47, Folder 8)
    - Austrian Labor Information- pub. in NYC (in German), undated (Box 47, Folder 9)
    - Bolshevik- Switzerland (in German), ca.Jan 1, 1933-Dec 1, 1933 (Box 47, Folder 10)
    - Das Banner des Leninist- Austria/Czechoslovakia (in German), May 1939-Jun 1939 (Box 47, Folder 11)
    - Bulletin Aux Militants(in French), Jan 1951, Feb 1951 (Box 47, Folder 12)
    - Bulletin Etudes Revolutionaries(in French), Jul 1947 (Box 47, Folder 13)
      Microfilm Reel Number 63
    - Bulletin of Information Zengakuren- Japan (in English), Jun 4, 1962 (Box 47, Folder 14)
    - Cahiers d'etude- ligue des communistes Internationalistes (in French), Apr 1935 (Box 47, Folder 15)
    - La Commune- Organe Central du Parti Cammmiste Internationaliste IV Int'l (in French), 1937-1938 (Box 47, Folder 16)
    - Communisme - Bulletin Mensuel par la Fraction Beige de la Gauche Communiste International(in French), Aug 1937, Sep 1937 (Box 47, Folder 17)
    - Communisme - Organe Theorique de L'organisation Communiste Revolutionaire(in French), Jul 1946 (Box 48, Folder 1)
      Microfilm Reel Number 64
    - Le Conmuniste - Organe Hebdomadaire de Groupe de L'opposition du P.C.B.(in French), Jan 1930-Sep 1930 (Box 48, Folder 2)
    - Le Communiste - Bulletin de la Gauche Communiste(in French), 1931-1933 (Box 48, Folder 3)
    - Daily Worker- annotated clippings including expulsion of Trotskyists, 1924, 1938, 1927 (Box 48, Folder 4-14)
      Microfilm Reel Number 64 (Reel 65 begins with folder 9)
    - L'Etincue(in French), Nov 1932-Jan 1933 (Box 48, Folder 15)
      Microfilm Reel Number 65
    - Die Fahne des Kormunismus(in German), Jan 1929-Apr 1930 (Box 48, Folder 16)
    - Freie Tribune(in German), 1952 (Box 48, Folder 17)
      Microfilm Reel Number 66
    - Der Funke(in German), Mar 1933 (Box 48, Folder 18)
    - Gegen den Storm- Organ of the KPD (in German), Sep 1930, Dec 1930 (Box 48, Folder 19)
    - Internasjonale(in Danish), Dec 1937 (Box 48, Folder 20)
    - International Press Correspondence, Jun 26, 1924 (Box 48, Folder 21)
    - L'Internationale(Union Communiste), Dec 1936 (Box 48, Folder 22)
    - Internationalisme - Gauche Communiste de France(in French), Jan 1947-May 1948 (Box 49, Folder 1)
    - L'Internationaliste - Organe de la fraction, undated (Box 49, Folder 2)
    - L'Internationaliste - Organe de la Gauche Communiste- France (in French), undated (Box 49, Folder 3)
    - Le Jeune Bolshevik(in French), undated (Box 49, Folder 4)
    - Junge Kampfer - Organe of KJVD (opposition)(in German), Dec 1929-Apr 1931 (Box 49, Folder 5)
    - Klarheit (Clarte) Internationalen Kommisten Deutschlands (in Exile)(in German), Jan 1935 (Box 49, Folder 6)
    - Klarheit (Clarte) - Organe de L'opposition Juive de Fauchi(pub. in France) (in Yiddish), 1930-1931 (Box 49, Folder 7)
    - La Knare Internacio Bulteno- (in Esperanto), internacia. Komunista frakcio de SAT (Trockista), 1950 (Box 49, Folder 8)
    - Die Kritische Parteistiniste, Dec 1932-Feb 1933 (Box 49, Folder 9)
      Microfilm Reel Number 67
    - La Lutte- pub. in Saigon (in French), 1938 (Box 49, Folder 10)
    - Mahnruf Organ der Kommmisten Links Opposition(in German), Aug 1932 (Box 49, Folder 11)
    - Le Militant- Workers Party of Australia, 1933-1938 (Box 49, Folder 12)
    - Le Militant- pub. in Saigon (in French), 1936 (Box 49, Folder 13)
    - Neue Front(in German), May 1938-Jun 1938 (Box 49, Folder 14)
    - Notre Bataille- Fraction de Gauche de Bagnolet (opposition) (in French), Mar 23, 1933 (Box 49, Folder 15)
    - Neue Internationale(in German), May 1947 (Box 49, Folder 16)
    - Oktober- (in Norwegian), 1937-1938 (Box 49, Folder 17)
    - Permanenter Revolution- Left opposition of KPD (in German), Mar 1932-Nov 1932 (Box 49, Folder 18)
    - Pro und Contra(in German), 1950-1953 (Box 49, Folder 19)
    - Le Redressment Commtmiste- Organ. de opposition (in French), 1928-1929 (Box 49, Folder 20)
      Microfilm Reel Number 68
    - Die Rote Faline- Internationalistislie Arbeiter partei - (French section) (in German), undated (Box 49, Folder 21)
    - Der Rote Kurier- der Linken opposition (in German), early1930s (Box 49, Folder 22)
    - Socialist Bulletin- Partai Socialis Indonesia (in English), 1957 (Box 49, Folder 23)
    - Solidarite et Liberte, Mar 1938 (Box 49, Folder 24)
    - The Spark- Organ of Workers Party of South Africa, May 1938-Jun 1939 (Box 49, Folder 25)
    - Soviet Des Usines- parti Ouvrier Internationaliste, 4th Int'l (in French), undated (Box 49, Folder 26)
    - Trotz Allendem- Organ. der Marzistischen Aktion der Schweiz - 4th Int'l (Switzerland) (in German), Feb 1935-Feb 1937 (Box 50, Folder 1)
    - Turning Point- Pub. by Communist League - U.S.A., Jun 1954 (Box 50, Folder 2)
    - L'Unite Leniniste - Organe des Bolsheviks - Leninists francais (opposition)(in French), Apr 12, 1928 (Box 50, Folder 3)
    - Unser Kampf- Pub. in U.S.A. by Communist League of America (Left opposition) (in Yiddish), 1932-1933 (Box 50, Folder 4)
      Microfilm Reel Number 69
    - La Voix Commmiste- section Belge de la Ligue Communiste Internationaliste (B-L) (in French), Sep 1934 (Box 50, Folder 5)
    - Wie Aufwarts?- International Communist League - Austria (in German), undated (Box 50, Folder 6)
  - PART D: HITLER'S RISE TO POWER
    - Statements - KPD - (Communist Party), SPD - (Social Dem. Party), SAP - (Left opposition-Trotskyists), Nazi, 1931-1933 (Box 50, Folder 7)
    - Periodicals (A) - Der Bolshewik - KPD, Der Leninist KPD, Spartaskusbriefe, KPD, 1931-1932 (Box 50, Folder 8)
    - Periodicals (B) Klassen front - (Left opposition of KPD), Signale (NAZI), Deutschland Erwachel (NAZI), Mitteilungsblatt (KPD), undated (Box 50, Folder 9)
    - Periodicals (C) Misc., 1931-1933 (Box 50, Folder 10)
    - Periodicals - SAZ (Sozialistische Arbeiter Zeitung) SAP (Socialist Workers Party - Left Opposition - Trotskyist), 1932-1933 (Box 50, Folder 11)
    - Periodicals - Leipziger Volkszeitung, Social Democratic Party, May 1931-Mar 1932 (Box 50, Folder 12)
    - Leaflets - KPD, SPD, NAZI, SAP, 1931-1932 (Box 50, Folder 13-15)
      Microfilm Reel Number 70
    - Unsere Stellung Zur K.P.D.-S.A.P. (Trotskyists), 1931-1932 (Box 50, Folder 16)
    - Clippings - KPD, SPD, SAP, NAZI, 1931-1933 (Box 50, Folder 17-18)
    - Estanpa (Spanish Periodical), Sep 1931 (Box 50, Folder 19)
      Microfilm Reel Number 71
    - Statement by Bolshevik/Leninist-International Left Opposition (in French and German), Aug 1932 (Box 50, Folder 20)
    - Communiste - Published by L'Humanite, 1932 (Box 50, Folder 21)
  - PART E: ADDENDA OF MISSING PAGES AND GRAPHIC MATERIALS (not microfilmed)
    - Red Cartoons from The Daily Worker(autographed by Robert Minor, Fred Ellis), 1926 (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - Krieg published by Neuer Deutscher Verlag: 7 original litho graphs by Otto Dix, G. Grosz, Otto Nagel, Kaethe Kollwitz, I. Krain, R. Schlichter, H. Zille, 1924 (Box 51, Folder 2)
    - "Images de la Chine Nouvelle",published by Les Editions Cercle d'Art, Paris. (lithographs), 1950s (Box 51, Folder 3)
    - Anti-Czar cartoons in Russian (scrapbook of 2 color newsclippings), ca.1917 (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - New Masses (bound, and inscribed by Mike Gold), May 1926-Oct 1926 (Box 51, Folder 5)
    - Missing pages: unidentified detached pages from the Shachtman archives., undated (Box 51, Folder 6)
- Series VI: Addendum (not microfilmed)
  For additional information, see also: Series I: Part E: American Left-Wing Opposition:Communist League of America (microfilm reel 3352, box 6) AND Series I: Part I: Socialist Party (microfilm reels 3370 & 3371, box 15)
  - Communist League of America Minutes, 1929-1931 (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - Communist League of America Minutes, 1932 (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - Communist League of America Minutes, 1933 (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - Young Socialist League of America: Includes correspondence of Bogdan Denitch, David McReynolds, Max Shachtman, 1953-1954 (Box 52, Folder 4)
  - Young Socialist League of America National Convention, 1955 (Box 52, Folder 5)
  - Young Socialist League of America National Convention, 1957 (Box 52, Folder 6)
- Series VII: Addendum 2 (unprocessed) (Box 53-58)